I had announced that
I would make another video
where I would discuss
such constellations as here.
Where a class stands in
composition relationship with two other classes.
I had already said that here, on
the one hand, only certain multiplicities are possible,
at this respective end for the
whole in such a part-whole relationship.
And I had already announced
that because of the additional requirement
that each part may only be
part of a whole, in composition relations
not all combinations of
multiplicities are necessarily useful here.
So one can write down all of them.
One can write here, multiplicity exactly
"1" shall prevail in each case.
But the question is:
Can this be filled with life
in a meaningful way in the sense
that we can specify objects for it?
And we can actually try
that for the time being.
So let's take this constellation.
And let's assume that there
is at least one C object.
Then this would mean that
such a C-object should exist here.
Let's call that small "c".
This is an object of the class C.
And because this exists, and
there are these relations here,
there must be also at
least one B-object in this case.
So exactly one B-object, to
which the C-object is related.
And exactly one A object, because
of the 1 at this composition end.
That means there would have to
be at least two more objects here.
Namely a B-object and an A-object.
And each of these would have
to be related to the C object.
Simply because of the composition
given above with the appropriate multiplicity.
And this would have the consequence that we
have here exactly constellations which are not allowed.
Namely, that a part, in the case of this
C-object, is at the same time part of several wholes.
And that is not allowed.
Therefore, what is written here on
this slide is not a legal situation.
So you would have been allowed to write this
up here, but you can never fill this with life.
That's why it doesn't make sense
to start with the modeling at all.
Then we look again at the case, how
it would be, if we
had decided differently at the beginning.
So we would have started with "0..1"
instead, for example here or
here on the other side.
Of course it doesn't
matter where we have "0..1".
Let's take this case and consider
how it would have looked like then.
Let's assume again that there
should be at least one C-object.
Let's specify that again.
And then, because of this
specification, there must also be an
A-object that is related
to the given C-object.
There must then be
such a connection here.
And now the question is:
What about the other composition?
What follows from this?
Well, it doesn't necessarily
require that a B-object exists.
Because "0..1" is there.
If you wanted to insert a B-object here
and connect it, then you
would have a problem, of course.
Then you would have the situation on the previous slide,
namely that you assign two integers to the C-object.
So you would not do that.
But you don't have to, because it
is also allowed (simply by the 0, which
stands here in the multiplicity)
not to have a B-object.
Only, if one does this,
then naturally also the question arises:
Why is there this composition
in this direction at all?
It will then never be
filled by anything with life.
That's why you could write
it down in that case,
but it wouldn't make any sense.
Because one would never actually
fill this C-B composition with life.
And then it's probably already
been wrong in the modeling
to even assume that that's there.
So that was the combination
where we have "1" and "0..1".
And then, of course, there
is at least one other possibility.
Namely, the situation where
we actually put "0..1"
on both ends
(for both compositions) here.
Then we can consider what might be
a reasonable assignment of these classes here.
Whether this is conceivable here, that
there is a part, which can
be part of two wholes, not
at the same time, but alternatively.
And in fact, you can think
of a situation here, for example.
Let's take our car examples again.
So let's say we somehow have a
class car and a class for wheels.
That will come up again
in the slides, a similar example.
Then, of course, a wheel can
be compositionally related to car, because
normally a wheel is mounted on a
car, and it's mounted on at most one.
And vice versa, one can
now add multiplicities to it.
A car can carry/contain 0..4 wheels.
On the slides before I
had nothing at the end.
So I would have assumed that it says
"0..*", i.e. any number of parts is allowed.
What would be the other
alternative for a wheel now?
Let's say, a wheel is mostly,
but not always, on a car.
For example, summer wheels are in
a wheel storage in the winter.
So let's say there
is another class "storage" here.
A wheel can also be in a storage,
and a storage can perhaps contain "0..20" wheels.
And now here it is quite conceivable that
a wheel is sometimes in the storage and
sometimes on a car, but is
never both at the same time.
That it is never at both at the
same time is not expressed by the multiplicities.
But simply by the additional
requirement that was on the slides.
Namely, that a part is never part of
more than one whole at the same time.
So here it would really be:
The wheel can be on a car.
The wheel can be in storage.
But only one of the two at a time.
So here that would be the
essential thing to hold on to.
But that's just dictated
by the modeling constraints and
by the language of how these
diagrams are to be interpreted in UML.
So then a wheel can never be on
a car and in storage at the same time.
Those were the three situations
for this constellation, each simply
with different multiplicities at
the top two ends.
And then on the slides there
was also something like this, this situation
where there are two classes that are
in compositional relation in a double way.
That's where I had also said:
What would not be allowed would be if this diamond
was somehow at the bottom instead of at the top.
That would be forbidden.
Then we would have a cyclic relationship.
That is forbidden.
But that, as it is shown here and
on the slides, was not forbidden per se.
One could certainly imagine that
there are somehow meaningful classes here.
Situations like here, requiring 1 in each
case, again, would not be particularly useful.
Because then an object of the
lower class could be related to
several objects of the upper class.
Namely once via this one
and once via the other composition.
This does not make much sense.
But for instance in the case that
we specify this with "0..1" at both
ends, one can well imagine
that there are meaningful instances.
You can think about what
might be conceivable classes here,
or what makes sense here.